Foreword

Devanahalli Venkataramanaiyya Gundappa, popularly known as DVG is often compared to an ashwattha tree (Ficus Religiosa) in the forest of Kannada renaissance which is both literary and cultural. In him we find many wonderful personalities that include a great scholar, ace journalist, profound socio-political thinker, cultural Messiah, literary master and a great humanist. He is simultaneously good and wise, self-less and humble, friendly and disciplined, traditional and modern, hearty and brainy and many more. He is one among those rare great sons of India too who played a remarkable role in its struggle for political and cultural freedom in an inimitably self-less manner. To sum up in one word, DVG is a modern Rsi of India in general and of Karnataka in particular.

Apart from his manifold social, political, cultural and the like service-activities, DVG wrote extensively in Kannada and English.

Especially his writings in Kannada that include a large variety prose and verse, rich in both quality and quantity, comprising of poems, plays, songs, translation, children literature, biographies, pen-portraits, memoirs; technical writings in the field of political science and journalism, philosophy and religion, poetics and criticism are a class by themselves and have stood the test of time. Thus he has naturally become one of the pioneers of Kannada literature in shaping and empowering it as a complete language.

Even today some of his prose and verse writings are best sellers and torch bearers in the area of beautifying the lives of one and all. They are equally appealing to both head and heart and endear the learned and the lay alike.

Baaligondu Nambike (Faith for Life) is DVG’s one of the most popular and profound works. In this, basing on his own contemplation of life, he has made a wonderful and equally successful attempt towards synthesizing as practical philosophy of life which is lucidly understandable and adoptable to one and all. In fact the author himself has stated in his foreword that this work is an honest attempt towards the realization of his own life’s purpose and process, faith and function.

The complete writing is very simple to understand lively to read and lovely to contemplate upon. Though the wisdom contained in it is sublime and eternal, no where the author has made it pedantic and preaching. In this short booklet, DVG has practically given the distilled philosophy of the East and the West that has paramount use in the way of leading a simple and sublime life. Nothing in this sweet work is impractical and nonspiritual. Every word is loaded and every leaf is a journey of joy. What the author has attempted in his other three great and well known works namely the Mankutimmana Kagga a poem, Jnaapakacitrashaale a memoir and Jeevanadharmayoga a scholarly study on the Bhagavad Gita, is succinctly summed up here.

Such a masterly writing is rendered in to English by my good friend Sri S M Haricharan. Hence he definitely deserves the wholehearted compliments of all those who are interested in enriching their lives. It is a long felt need of many and that has been aptly fulfilled by him. The sad part of the modern Indian youth is the absolutely zero knowledge of the masterly writings of the savants in the regional languages. Due to this ignorance, they are often going to the cheap and corrupt western versions of our classical wisdom. Least to say that it is highly deplorable and when such is the situation, it is very heartening that qualified and sensible youngsters like Mr. Haricharan are coming forward to take this task of mirroring the masters of Indian languages in to readable English and help the less-privileged. Sri Haricharan, apart from being a technocrat, a serious student of Indian culture and literature. His interests in music and philosophy too are commendable. His present task of taking DVG through his little classic Baaligondu Nambike to the larger world of English-readers is rewarding in many ways and I take this opportunity to congratulate him for this labor of love. May such efforts of him and the like increase and perpetuate not only the memory of DVG, but also of many masters like him.

Shataavadhani Dr. R. Ganesh

Preface

This book is a translation of one of the most prolific thinker, literary wizard of Karnataka Dr. D.V. Gundappa (fondly remembered as DVG). The original book written in is collection of essays and articles written by Dr. D.V.G and published in the then leading dailies in the near post independence period of 1950. The questions that are raised are highly thought provoking and just provide a glimpse of what a great visionary and social thinker he was. It is hard to believe that some of them even now are relevant and haunt us as responsible citizens of this country. It tries to shake us from our comfort zone that we all have established as self-centered individuals and take the ownership of contributing to larger part of society and thereby putting the entire nation on a progressive path.

Each time I have read the original work it has startled me as to how execution of some of the recommendations could have helped our nation in shunning the developing nation tag and put itself to strongly compete with the economic powers. The articulations used by the author to identify the differences existing between the western civilization and us and thereby suggest a path that is conducive yet result yielding is simply superb.

My humble attempt at translation of this great work is more of self gratifying experience to share with larger audience which has English as second language invariably. The spark to take up this project came when Dr. R. Ganesh mentioned as to what a huge benefit it could be if the original work were to be available in English. By stating this, I have no right to take the credit of bringing this for benefit to the society and nor is there a need to demonstrate the intellectual strength and the social contribution Dr. DVG rendered during his lifetime. It is quite magnanimous and he will be recollected for centuries to come through innumerable works, the gem of which being Mankuthimmana Kagga.

This journey of translation that I undertook has transformed me for better and helped me to set in right objectives for myself. It is this benefit that I would like to pass on to you when you read this work. I am joyous and thankful that you already have taken first step in this direction by picking up this book for reading. The book is not intended to any selective audience but to each one of us who have the innate desire to achieve and build something that is impactful for larger part of society and which is beyond our selfish desires and passions. You, as a reader may be of any sex, be in any profession or of any socio-economic background and any age, this reading will compel you to rethink and reorient for better personal and professional life. This is definitely not a self-help book or is aimed to drive home any philosophy. It will serve you to wake up to some hard facts that can be an eye opener for taking positive action.

First, I need to thank Gokhale Institute of Public Affairs and Shri S R Ramaswamy, Honorable Secretary of GIPA for benevolently allowing me to go ahead with the publication and printing of this translation work.

I am deeply indebted and thankful to Dr. R. Ganesh who has been my inspiring Guru and has taken pain to review and obliged with a Foreword for this book. It was his remark during one of our study circle discussions that kindled my thought to take up this task.

My friends in personal and professional life who have impacted my thought process directly or indirectly during this period of translation.

My special thanks to Mr. Pranesh Siravara, MD of Prism Books and his entire team for accepting to publish work of a novice like me. Their encouragement and support has helped me to humbly offer this book to all you readers.

Of course, it would definitely not have been possible without the encouragement and support of my immediate family – Anna, Amma, Chethan, Shilpa and Sarvajeeth.

– S.M. Haricharan

Life

How mean am I when Life gives me gold and I
give you silver, and yet I deem myself generous.

-Kahlil Gibran

What is Life? Why Life? What do we live for? Do we live to die or is there any higher meaning to our Life? The great Saint Kanakadasa has said the following:

“Every work done by every individual in this world is to satisfy the three basic needs food, shelter and clothing. We often speak kind words to impress others and lie to each other to curry out materialistic gains. People assume various roles and behave pretentiously it is only for sake of above benefits.”

So should we conclude and sum it up that this is the mystery of life.

In our houses the livestock, pets, roaches and rodents all live for this purpose. All animals dwelling in the forest, birds in the sky and all other living beings live to satiate their stomach, strengthen their shelter and seek sweetness of love. No living being can escape the thoughts of food, sleep, companionship and overcoming fear of death which are common to all. What one needs to examine and introspect is whether the fate of human- being is being confined to such thoughts like other animals or is he higher to them in any aspect? Is there an objective or goal to humanbeing higher than striving for food, shelter and clothes?

If we look at people around us it doesn’t seem or appear that any such questions cross minds of at least fifty per cent of them. Most of them live like any other animal striving hard day in day out without a higher purpose in life. They finally rest in peace without having made any impact or impression to the external world of their existence. It is very apt to recollect what Isaac Asimov mentioned in Encyclopedia of Science & Technology which is that one in 6 million who have walked on this earth have managed to leave footprints behind them and rest of have just passed like insects.

Is this the right thing to do? Is there any other noble thought or purpose of life that can be identified by us?

Individual Goals

In this world there are innumerable people and all of them are different. Difference is not only in the physical form or appearance but also in their mannerisms and behavior. As we observe that the distribution of the various organs in the human body is in the same proportions with respect to different individuals there are subtle differences which makes us to distinctly identify. Even when the individual is not directly in front of us we are able to recognize by his voice or may also be from few mannerisms which every individual would have built. The differences are not essentially on the physical aspects but also on the other features or attributes the individual possesses such as responses of the sensual organs coupled with characteristic differences such as one being more arrogant, friendly, and compassionate or likes and dislike. At the macro level there are differences in the individual on the socio-economic aspect varying from someone being poor to extremely rich.

Like this, individuals across the world have some common attributes on the physical, psychological and socio-economic front and differences which makes them unique. Therefore every individual has to pretty much decide and mould his life accordingly on his own. There cannot be a single goal and single path for all individuals. One goal and one path or means to achieve it for everyone is improbable. The goal that Kanakadasa had set for himself could not be envisaged by others during his period. Goal and path to achieve that is distinct for every human being.

Can I identify the most appropriate goal for myself drawing inspiration from experiences of life or with help of a Guru (teacher) or through study of great books? The answer to this is all the above sources are like a huge super market. Supermarket is stuffed with variety of goods from groceries to garments, technology products to home furnishings etc. We all visit and shop based on our needs and ability to buy (money available for spend). Likewise we need to select the goal and path to achieve that by weighing the situation we are in and the competency one has. Guru or Books or experiences of life only are raw materials and function as a direction post helping the individual with various options. But, we are the individuals who need to achieve that goal and walk the path to achieve it and therefore we need to exercise our discretion here.

Goal gets built incrementally and can never be a onetime exercise. When we are in the house our goal is the foot of the hill, once we reach the foot the hill-top will be the goal, as we reach the hill-top, temple on the hill becomes the goal and once you reach the entrance of the temple, getting to the sanctum sanctorum becomes the goal. So goal is essentially a series of goals which gets built in this fashion. As and when we progress towards achieving a goal, a higher goal calls to be conquered. The most important process in this is identifying the first goal. In which direction should we set forth our journey becomes the fundamental question that needs to be addressed.

Human Purpose

For a human being there could be four good intentions or purposes as identified by the spiritual leaders which are i) Dharma – righteousness, duty, morality ii) Artha – wealth, prosperity iii) Kama – wish, desire iv) Moksha – liberation. Human desires, thoughts and efforts are innumerable. Whatever they may be they can be classified under any one of them. Out of these four the first three are applicable to any individual who is leading a householder’s life.

Dharma – means good conduct – it is the blossoming of the soul. We already have seen as how do we identify or define something as good. The conduct of ours which causes no harm to any individual around us, which can beautify the life of others and in the process can beautify our own life, can be termed as good conduct i.e. dharma. It should have the capability to nurture everyone’s life not of a single individual. It should also help him to uplift himself and maintain equilibrium with the society. Dharma encompasses truth, purity, righteousness & empathy. Likewise it is inclusive of holy deeds such as mediation, offering prayer, rituals, sacrifices, charity & social responsibility. It is challenging to comprehend the meaning of dharma in the classical context but its forms are cognizable to the mental faculty of common people. For many civilizations it has stood its ground, grown and has become widely recognized. Manu’s following words serve as the standard for Dharma:

Dhriti Kshama Damo Asteyam Shaucham Indriyanigrahah
Dheer Vidya Satyam Akrodho Dashakam Dharma Lakshanam

The ten important features of Dharma being : (1) Dhriti – Patience, (2) Kshama – Forgiveness, (3) Damah – Self Control, (4) Asteya – Not Stealing, (5) Shaucha – Purity, (6) Indriya Nigraha – Sense Control, (7) Dhi – Intellect, (8) Vidya – Learning/ Knowledge, (9) Satya – Truth, (10) Akrodha – Absence of Anger.

Artha (Wealth) – Artha represents money, land, gold, stones and other forms of wealth. If the right order for life is dharma then food and clothing form the foundation of it. The ways and means to earn this is in dharma. But wealth has the inherent characteristic to command things. Some kinds of foods have the ability to provide strength but they need to be consumed in limit. If we consume more we get intoxicated and so is the case with wealth. If we accumulate more than what is required for our right living then it leads to intoxication and ultimately loose dharma. So to create wealth in such a fashion is a duty according to dharma. Vedas therefore suggest not abstaining from creation of such wealth: “Boothyaiyna pramaditavyam, tatho me shriyamaavah”

Kama - Kama means desire. It is the desire for comfort and happiness more than the admiration of life. Love, Friendship, high quality food, beauty, music, dance, and movies are all different aspects of desire. Like how a person who indulges in creation of wealth can be led to eventually deviation from dharma (righteousness) same would result in over indulgence in these desires. Desire which is unharmful has a significant place in the system of dharma. Enjoying comfort is no sin and so is experiencing happiness, but one cannot forget dharma.

Both wealth and desire need to function in a well-defined boundary, which means there is enough of freedom for one to exercise. Both of these are origin points for development of mental faculty and human efforts. This influences the creation and growth of human civilization which encompasses science, commerce, occupation, industries, technology, social order & relationship between societies. If wealth and Kama help in expansion of life it is dharma which provides the required treatment to keep this expansion healthy.

Moksha (Salvation) – Salvation or Nirvana as it is called in the recent times is a subject which is farfetched for experience of humans. The above three are cognizable by us in our daily life. Moksha belongs to a different class all together and gets a distinct treatment. It is specially attached to saints, individuals detached from society and spiritual leaders. Dharma, Artha and Kama create a connection and bonding to the society we all live in. This connection over a period of time makes us go through turmoil of experiences. This is the difficulty of bonding and getting released from such kind of bonding which passes through ages is salvation. For humans the thought of the supreme soul and consistent meditation on it, provides a protective shield against the sufferings he undergoes. An individual who recognizes and comprehends that supreme energy which is omnipresent has the ability to understand the value of the materialistic world and stay detached from such kind of superficial existence. The attainment of such a supreme state is called Moksha or salvation. For the purpose of this book, Moksha is not so important but has been touched upon has one of the four human purposes.

Life’s Enthusiasm

We should first identify the lacuna or defect in us which upon correction can lead us to eradicate all other difficulties. This can act only through ruthless act of introspection or self discovery. If we do this we will recognize that for generations together we have rendered our mind weak, unwisely detached from action and have lost all the courage and energy. We have to transform this weak mind to a stronger one.

It is also not that there have never been attempts to improve the quality of life. India has seen visionaries such as Sir M Visweswaraiah, Dr. Verghese Kurien, Vikram Sarabhai, Prof. Satish Dhawan, Dr. APJ Abdul Kalam and others who have effectively used the government structure, system and policies to reach out to common man and uplift their quality of life. We have created world class organizations in the last two decades in areas of Information Technology & Bio-technology through leadership of Narayan Murthy, Azim Premji, Kiran Mazumdar Shaw and Ratan Tata to name a few. There is also a huge spurt in the entrepreneurship across sectors which is an encouraging sign and can hold a promising future for this country. But, what is more important is for a nation with current size of population and ever growing, there needs to be a multifold effort and reforms that need to take place in the hearts and minds of every citizen of this country. Any country which has progressed well has done not merely because of its leaders but the positive energy kindled in every heart and mind of its citizen which working towards a larger common vision.

A Formidable Story

In the city of Kalyanpur there lived a wealthy person who had constructed a huge bungalow and had got a well dug in its premises. They couldn’t find water in spite of having dug for 70 – 80 ft in the ground. As he was pondering what to do with it, situation had arrived for him to meet his lawyer friend in city of Chennai and at the same time this friend was considering to settle down in Kalyanpur for reasons of health. The friend asked the wealthy person whether he could help him to locate a nice bungalow for him and also insisted that he needed one which has a well that could be used for some religious activities. The wealthy person responded said that he was aware of a newly constructed bungalow of someone he knew and it indeed had a well whose water was very sweet. So the friend indicated to him that he would visit the following Saturday for looking at the bungalow in Kalyanpur. Meanwhile the wealthy person put all the effort to fill the well to a substantial level with clean and sweet water. Finally the bungalow was sold for a huge amount. Within weeks of the friend occupying the bungalow, water in the well started drying up and after few more weeks the water completely dried up. How long can a well have water which has been artificially pumped from an external source?

A human’s life and country’s prospect is also similar. They cannot sustain and grow from the support received by friends or the external borrowings from neighbors. Energy needs to take birth and grow from within or else any magnitude of help received from outside will not help. Like spring of water in the well, energy and enthusiasm needs to constantly spring out and drive the individual and the country.

It is bewildering to see only few human beings taking such a initiative and leaders of country not having a big heart and higher aspirations to accomplish that is beneficial for everyone.

Era of Loss of Courage

Like this when different religions which started and continued their journeys in different directions it might have witnessed drastic changes. Any religion or philosophy cannot grow getting confined inside a cave as it has to set its sight on the human civilization. Religion is there to create a social order in this world and world should not be created for sake of religion. Every establisher of religion may have found the necessity for a new religion by observing the social conditions present then. The greatest motivation for him was from the dissatisfaction seen in the society. There seems to be a major shakeup which took place around 2500 years in the social system of our ancestors and this could be the reason for transforming a mind which was having a winning attitude to one of losing one.

There could be many reasons which could have led to such a big change in the social system. Natural disasters, politically led activities, invasions and attacks of the foreigners, prolonged famine may have contributed to shattering of the human mind. When the mind mellowed down a great person may have taken birth whose high intellect or mesmerizing oratory skills or noble conduct or some other human influence could have risen him to fame and he could have shown a new vision and have led people in that direction. This should have occurred even before the era of Mahavir or Gautama Buddha. Voice of joy and happiness of the Aryan race came down and voice of helplessness gained momentum.

The other reason could have been prolonged indulgence in the enjoyment of victory and luxury leading to lack of practice of positive energy giving way to hardships and difficulties and eventually creating a changed mindset. Let us all recollect a common experience of the world. A person who was born poor attains wealth and fame in society because of his intellectual capabilities and physical effort. When he dies he leaves the family in the wealth and comfort created by him. If we assume that his children also engage in further growth of wealth, in the following generations of his grandchildren or great-grandchildren they start neglecting the primary attributes for creation of this wealth and also fail to put their individual effort. Further, all these result in enjoyment of created wealth, animosity among the family members, unhappiness finally getting engulfed in poverty and decline. As is the famous quote “Seeds of failure are embedded in the greatest moments of success” so will be the attitude of people who have been gifted with success and wealth rather than they would have deservingly earned. It could be therefore suggested that our ancestors who had toiled hard to create a mind of strength and courage was uprooted by the later generations and developed a mindset of defeat.

Long before the period of Sri Adi Shankaracharya (prior to 800 AD), enthusiasm had decreased in life and thinking such as this living world is inferior, human life gets afflicted with difficulties, human body and sensual pleasures are condemning, enjoyment is sin and not to be expected and if there is anything that is real it is the external world and even superior to this is Moksha or salvation, had crept in.

“End this human birth and cycle of such creations” is the song that is being taught to us by our elders.

Courageous Intellect

A journey which embarked to seek victory and satisfy aspirations of life by Vedas gradually led to think about external philosophy and divided it into two branches. One branch which relied on logic reached desert and dried up. The other one has travelled like a flood encompassing everything on its way. It is our duty for us to research and identify the river which existed before this branch out and lead it into our life. Therefore let us look at the Upanishads.

One is Ishopanishad which states as:

“This world is embedded in God. Therefore all this is property of God. In this context you should not presume anything as yours; you should use it treating all this as his divine gift. You are entitled to receive that based on the work you perform. For that reason you need to perform well. Give me the mind to live for hundred years by performing the work with all wisdom and enthusiasm and eat the fruits gifted by the Lord.”

The other is Taittiriya Upanishad which says as follows:

“Be cautious not to commit mistake in comprehending truth or speaking truth. Behave similarly with respect to Dharma. Be alert in achieving whatever is good. Conduct yourself well in the righteous manner in creation of wealth, with respect to elders, with relatives and friends and let your actions be filled with wise knowledge. Let you create abundantly food grains and other materials required for life. All things which have form and substance are all part of God. Therefore if you consider all transactions and business as service to God, divine gift of God then you will experience and reach abode of God.

Bhagavad-Gita which is considered as the essence (or summarized text) of all Upanishads says the following:

“If you have to fight for Dharma, go out, stand and fight; do not run away from situation. Dharma means principle of holding all living things in a state of equilibrium. If you fight for your personal benefit or cause you will get imprisoned in it. A person who sacrifices the attitude of 'I', 'It’s mine', 'My happiness', 'My welfare', 'My prestige', 'My name' and works for the well being of everyone will have all his obstacles removed and enable growth of his soul. Entire world is filled with Brahman. If you work with intention of benefiting the society and as an offering to God, it will bring you prosperity. Therefore lead your life for the world; experience and tolerate victory and loss with equal measure. Analyze the situation and act. Work and be victorious as a disciple of Lord Shiva.”

Such a mental attitude is what is primarily required.

Importance of Life

Life is a huge subject. It is most sacred and deserves all respect. For a life to germinate and take its birth the creator would have made many preparations prior to it. We need to constantly rethink about it. In plants, in lizards, snakes, reptiles, fishes and other animals there are strange mechanisms devised by nature to enable reproduction. Human body is an astonishing machine. It is filled with chemical elements which drive it, chemicals such as human mind. It is created with various such mechanisms, hard labor of patience and love by God. To call that inferior and ignoring is not a wisely act. To respect this life and lead it to a good position with all possible efforts is a dharmishta (follower of dharma). Every life is a hidden treasure of innumerable energies. A life, whose such hidden or inherent energy gets enriched, strengthened and becomes available for welfare of mankind will become successfully complete. Therefore it is inappropriate to be unenthusiastic with respect to life. There has to be devotion and interest with respect to all matters of life.

Inappropriate Detachment

Songs of philosophy, hymns about various gods, verses written by servants of god all preach detachment which is inappropriate and easily attainable. Such a detachment is restricted to words and of complete inaction. It only helps to build laziness, cowardly seclusion and detachment born out of inability. “Nothing is possible from me; everything is controlled and managed by someone else. What is the use of you struggling? Do not strain yourselves unnecessarily; just sit and keep meditating on God” is the common thing preached by divine songs of god. Added to this are the songs of dejection which proclaim “what is the point in comforting this human body equivalent to log of wood?” In the very first instance people are facing hardships and are subjected to poverty and on top of it if this so called divine songs preach “do not worry about what’s happening, you be where you are as what can you accomplish you are just a human being” they get easily influenced to them leaving behind their responsibilities and duties. Such is the intoxication provided by the commoner’s philosophy.

Detachment means to forego the selfish interest in worldly things. “Nothing is mine, everything belongs to God”, not to beg for ones’ own comfort, not troubling any one is real detachment and such a detachment is purified by wisdom. But, for a person where there is nothing in this world that belongs to him and is toiling hard daily to satiate his stomach, where can he find detachment? If he wants to have detachment from life (breadth or life giving force) the life itself does not allow happening and demands to be with the human body. Apart from life there is nothing that a poor person can sacrifice and be detached from life. If you have not kept anything for yourself then there is nothing to be sacrificed and so a poor man does not have anything at his disposal for sacrifice. Preaching detachment to such a person is futile and would be adding to agony of his life. Feeding the patient with food which is tasteful to tongue and advising poor people to sit idle would be leading them to misery and not out of it.

We should first stop cribbing about our Fate and develop a courageous outlook. Bring smiles back to our face giving up crying, weak and loosing mind should be replaced with intellect to win, cowardly detachment should go and valiant effort should come in.

What do we mean by Devotion to God?

Does it mean that we do not require devotion to God? It is a redundant question. No one is saying that we do not require devotion to God. But, the question here is in understanding the right kind of devotion. Devotion means display of holy ash, vermilion, necklace of holy beads, traditional trident, sacred pendants is the thinking of many people. Endless chanting of Rama, Shiva (Hindu Gods) and singing holy songs at temples are the main characteristics of devotion is the opinion of few. These practices and principles are bad and are futile is not anyone’s contention. But our stance is these are not sufficient. Let there be singing of divine songs and wearing of holy objects as this might provide some kind of solace and strength to few human minds. Just as we decorate our houses with colorful paints, flowers and leaves during festival and auspicious occasions, holy chanting and ornamentation can bring some radiance to life. But decoration alone does not make it a festival there needs to be some good food prepared in the house for the occasion. This means devotion needs to have more of wisdom driven efforts along with holy chanting. Devotion does not mean mental turbulence alone but also include human efforts. Devotion means an emotion which originates from heart and emerges out of our throat is an old feeling. Devotion is energy of soul that originates in our head and gets out through our hands is our opinion. The seat of devotion is heart is a thinking of past, devotion’s one foot is in heart and the other is in our intellect is our thinking. Devotion should reach God is the belief of past, devotion is created by God, he is a witness to it and it should reach the human world is our opinion. It does not suffice if devotion evokes good words from our mouth but it should elicit good work from us. That good work should have the capability to serve larger part of society we live in. We believe human effort is main component of devotion.

If we observe in this limelight just as we regard Purandaradasa, Kanakadasa, Saint Kabir, Basavanna, Nijaguna Shivayogi, as great devotees in the same league are Kempegowda (founder of Bengaluru), Dadabhai Naoroji, Ranade, Rangacharlu, Gokhale, Tilak, Gandhi, JC Bose, P C Ray, J N Tata, Sir M Visweswaraiah who have rendered yeoman services to society. People who have created better constitution and government, who have worked for upliftment of poor, people who were responsible for spread of science and technology, establishment of research and development centers thereby fostering newer technologies, developed new machines and intellectual property for benefit of society should also be considered as devotees. If one’s devotion is expressed through tears, devotion of other’s is through strengthened efforts.

We should approve mental attitude which is supported by science and human capabilities that is responsible for such a cognizable devotion.

What is Science?

In their essence there can be no conflict between science and religion. Science is a reliable method of finding truth. Religion is the search for a satisfying basis for life…. Yet a world that has Science needs, as never before, the inspiration that religion has to offer…. Beyond the nature taught by science is the spirit that gives meaning to life.

-Dr. Arthur H. Compton

The purpose of science is to question about this universe, experiment, research and search for answers to why is this? How is this? The knowledge that results out of such a search is Science. Without becoming a blind faith, knowledge which originates of independent thinking and review is Science.

Students of Science need to work primarily in three areas:

Different forms of object
Classification of objects
Inter-relationship between objects

Every object in this universe needs to be analyzed for its form, size, weight, color, properties, fundamental elements which the object is made of and their behavioral nature. So, the fundamental duty of science is gathering data of each of the above parameters and analyzing them.
Second duty of science is classification of objects based on the properties and creating taxonomy. At the broad level they can be classified as living and non-living. In living you have terrestrial, aquatic, amphibians, living in air; in terrestrial we have humans, animals, insects and so on as specific classes; in non-living we have metals, salts, gases, fuels and so forth as special classes. Such a systematic classification enables us to reasonably understand and recognize the basic features and properties of most of objects.

Such diversely classified objects influence each other by enhancing, negating, decreasing the fundamental properties of the other object and work of science is to reason out as to how and why this happens. Such a mutually influencing phenomenon between objects has transformed this universe into a great place and has divinely held together. The intricate study of such inter-relationship has been helpful tool and utility in our daily life.

Science is such a vast subject which is growing daily and ever expanding. The main feature of science is its independent examination of subject. Fearless and Unbiased research of Universe is Science.

Inter-relationships between objects are infinite and therefore there is a limitation in our effort for understanding this as it is. Therefore science needs to endlessly continue its pursuit of truth and can never claim that it has reached its goal. Such a goal is a temporary destination with respect to time, environment and capabilities of the researcher.

Limitation of Science

Nobody can claim everything is possible through Science. There are many questions beyond the realm of Science and is left unanswered. The mystery surrounding the basic tenet of life and mind is yet unconquered by science. With all the technology advancements in science in Europe it couldn’t prevent the world wars and destruction to mankind. Everybody agrees that only strengthening Science is insufficient for positive progress of society and at the same time we need to agree that we can’t let go of it.

Science is just a tool like Weapon or Wealth. Weapon can be used to protect lives and at the same time is put into use by criminals to kill; weapon by itself is neither good nor bad. Good or bad is dependent on the hands in which it rests. Wealth similarly can be used for charity and to create violence it all depends on the individual prudence.

Just because a few ill intentioned people use wealth for wrong causes no one aspires to be poor. As weapons have been put into use for mass destruction by Western countries we cannot refrain from building such technologies.

Goodness without strength is a cry of helplessness. Mother has natural love towards her child but when the child is ill; her crying will do no good or cure its illness. At that point of time presence of mind of mother to get an able doctor saves child. It is not mother’s cry but power of science which proves to be appropriate. We first require wisdom than the God’s kindness. How did the difficulty or challenge arise and what is the right response for it is result of scientific research. We should therefore take up all our life’s questions and review it in most scientific manner.

Ethiopia, historically known as Abyssinia was a country with good citizens whose patriotism was no lesser than any other country’s citizens. They were naturally courageous people but all they lacked was scientific advancement. On October 3rd 1935, Italian army under leadership of Benito Mussolini attacked Ethiopia. War experts had predicted that Mussolini would require four lakh soldiers and four years to conquer this country. But on May 5th 1936, Italy was successful in establishing its dominance over Ethiopia. Ethiopia had natural defense in its mountains, forests, valleys and land terrain which made it difficult for soldiers but Italy with a small army strongly supported by latest defense equipments such as aircrafts and other machinery was victorious in seven months. The greatest lesson learnt from this is no amount of natural resources and ability will be sufficient without backing up of Science and Technology.

Even today in few parts of India when they are attacked by diseases such as Cholera, Chicken Pox people in villages rush to temple of goddess rather than getting it attended by physicians. One needs to understand that without disturbing one’s faith it is equally important to get help of science.

Pump and Pray

Few Englishmen were travelling in a mid-sized ship. The ship suddenly encountered huge waves and storm which made water rush into the ship. Sailors got frightened by this and becoming directionless went to Father who was sitting on deck and sought help. Father asked them what should he do and everyone said that they all need to pray together and he should lead them. Father quickly responded why they had become so dejected and ignored them. After sometime the voices of sailors seeking help became even more prominent. Father than advised, Pray but, keep pumping the water and pray. This may just be a story but lesson for us is “God helps those who help themselves”. Self effort and God’s help are interwoven and they cannot stand alone. Human beings have been gifted by God with intellect. This entrusts him with responsibility to effectively use this intellect. But men cannot shift this responsibility back to God’s shoulders it is uncalled for. Men have to execute their responsibility and leave the rest to God.

Science – Boon or Bane

As we require medicine to cure us from diseases, likewise application of science is essential to solve every other challenge of life. We have effectively used this technology to provide information for farmers in selection of seeds, fertilizers, irrigation techniques, and climatic warnings and how to preserve the harvest. This has helped us to transform the yield in several years but there is far more scope for penetration of tools and techniques for continued growth.

Garment industry has transformed itself in last six decades of independence from traditional industry to use of sophisticated machinery. Human power with textile machineries has made it possible for India to become leading exporters ($ 24 billion in 201011).

India today has witnessed global manufacturing and services industries set up their research and production facilities which have boosted economic lives of its people and access to latest technologies.

In this context we have to recognize and stress the role of teachers across country to create a sharp mindset of adapting to Science and Technology for betterment of society. We need to have a scientific order and temperament in every household.

World has witnessed unimaginable spurt in newer technologies in last three decades as internet and mobile are gaining ground in every house. We have successfully used this to make travel arrangements, take timely medical help and make business worldwide sitting in the remote corners of this country. We are yet to see unleash of far better technologies which can improve our quality of life.

In the same breadth what we also have to bring to our cognizance is just as we see Science can achieve greater things it is not free of boundary. Science is more an extrinsic phenomenon and can change things external to us. It has more power and control on our senses. But, what is farfetched to these sensual organs is our inner world. We can only take a guess at working of inner world but will not be able to measure through scientific instruments. If we break open our brain we will not be able to find any trace of our thought process and nor there is a way to get a microscopic view of what is happening in an individual’s brain. In this manner what is transacting in one’s heart is only a guess but not visible to anyone to prove it. This makes it difficult for science to answer to take us to root of our life.

In the beginning of Scientific Era, looking at success received by Science, few people felt that there is nothing impossible that cannot be achieved by science. But, in 50-60 years it was realized that it is inappropriate to have such over ambitious goals. There are many mysteries which are inexplicable through Science is an accepted fact by many renowned scientists. There are no theories in science to explain concept of soul, God, Karma (causal act - cycle of cause and effect). There are many scientists who are experimenting around this but it is hard to find a consensus among them to define any of this. There have been more of logical arguments and counter arguments. Subject which is invisible to eyes of science is philosophy which is nothing but Vedanta or spiritual science. It deals with God, Good, Evil (Bad), Heaven, Hell, life after death, interrelationship between souls, result of previous action, salvation and other such mystic things.

In this way there is something mysterious that is external to science but attached to it. To be more precise, Science in itself holds many mysterious things which are not alien to Vedas or Vedanta. There are things which are explicit and implicit in sway of God. The supreme object is having form as well is formless. According to Vedanta it is mutable and immutable. Accordingly there are things which human intellect can comprehend and which are incognizant. It is our duty to stretch ourselves as much as possible putting in the best efforts. It is also our duty to acknowledge and accept those things as God’s intent which is unattainable in spite of his efforts. In a wise man’s path both scientific effort and patience to destiny are interwoven. In his life courage and detachment stay connected. For his faith, self-confidence is one eye and the other is devotion to God.

We can visualize a situation which involves power of science, devotion to God and human intellect. If someone in our house is inflicted with a disease what do we do? We will consult among family and friends and visit a capable and efficient doctor. The ability to consult, search and identify the appropriate doctor is human intellect. After thorough examination of the patient, doctor prescribes the necessary medicine and advices him to consume the same in a prescribed manner. This is power of Science. We advice the patient to trust the doctor and follow doctor’s prescription as what is required to get cured along with medicines is the mental strength and belief in doctor’s advice. Mind has control over body and hence they also represent a part of medicine. With this sentiment our ancestors said :

“Oushadham Jaahnavi Toyam Vaidyo Narayano Harihi”. This medicine is holy water (Ganges) and doctor who has prescribed it is God himself. This is a congregation of Intellect-Science-Devotion.

As we have one dimension as human effort, second as the scientific knowledge, the third dimension is morality. That is Goodness and that is dharma (righteousness). Dharma or Righteousness is a conduct which results in reduction of torment among the living beings and increase of mutual co-operation in life. All living beings whose human conduct follows an order or assumes a well accepted social relation is dharma. If scientific intellect combines itself with consciousness of dharma then there will be glow of life.

As Ethiopia is a witness to a country which was high on moral grounds or righteousness but lacked scientific temperament or knowledge, so was Germany in pre-world war era which had all the necessary scientific knowledge but lacked righteousness. Both of them lead to disasters. The constant war to own most powerful weapons by countries in World and cold war in other countries is a proof for scientific advancement without righteousness.

India fortunately has traversed this path in a well balanced model of scientific growth coupled with disarmament for destruction. But what is disheartening is to see sporadic events of violence in various parts of country or using the scientific advancements for unlawful benefits. We have become susceptible to use ways and means which appear easy to be employed to gain on personal front. We easily emulate their mannerisms and behavior that looks convenient but fail to understand the core values present in their philosophy or their ethos.

Distress of Villages

There is an important thing that needs to be said to people residing in villages. People speaking at political rallies and news journalists have a practice to describe rural citizens as highly innocent. They are uneducated, therefore are innocent, free of deceit and are honest are the general praise showered on them. This is a matter of exaggeration. People who graze cattle are not embedded with kindness and innocence of them. There was a time when our ancestors did their transactions keeping Sun and Moon as the witness, taking oath keeping one’s hand on the other and were retracting to swear untruth in front of idols in temple. That era is far behind us now. There are ample people who are aware of law and few lawyers in every nook and corner of the country. Lawyers are dime and dozen who offer advice at convenience and therefore people in villages take the superficial knowledge of law as sufficient for them. Over and above the ethical conduct has two dangers I) they are economically backward and there is a natural urge to somehow make money as there is saying “Daridra doshena karothi papam”, because of poverty we are instigated to create sin. II) Sense of social ignominy is also less among ruralites than the urbanites. Conduct of the urbanites cannot escape the public attention and getting into news. Transactions in villages happen secretly and are never published. For these reasons untruth, deceit, cunningness and superficial behavior are not uncommon in villages. One can find lot of such evidence lying in courts rural areas. There are ample incidents of group clashes and violence which have retarded the growth of villages. All these are not part of moral conduct.

As we showcase and uphold the bad character of ruralites we should not forget that their teachers and leaders are urbanites. As the universal opinion prevails that urbanites are most civilized and supreme beings, it is but natural for our rural population to emulate them. Our urban society’s main feature is to dwell in glory of wealth - which strongly believes money alone has the capability to buy anything in this world and lives with this false prestige.

Agrarian Economy

In Agrarian economy food grains was very important. The power of notes and coins was not so dominant then. Sumptuous food, clothing enough to cover body, treasury filled with grains, barn filled with cattle was the sole purpose of our ancestors and today’s villagers believe money is strength and their purpose is to have cash in hand and cash in bank. They have learnt this from urbanites. Person who first created money a mesmerizing tool also needs to be credited with creation of all evil things of the civilization. The atrocities and clashes that have taken place because of this person has not been caused by no other individual. In agrarian based economy such kind of destruction is not possible as grains cannot be hoarded for a longtime as it will get rotten and no one can hoard large quantities escaping notice of others. One has to utilize the food grains in one form or the other. But, when currency rules the economy, one has the ability to reserve the wealth in whatever form and wherever possible in most secretive manner. Materialistic comforts and luxury which cannot be purchased through grains can be easily obtained by money. This creates a greed for money and desire to acquire wealth by whatever means. Government officers, Lawyers, Professors, Businessman and every other class of people have all chosen this path. So, how long can our friends living in villages be free of such thoughts and action?

For creation of wealth, people living in cities choose different means and employ various methods which are not easily visible. People living in villages employ other methods which are little crude and noticeable. Deceit groups, rivalry, disputes, corruption, pomp and show are present in wealthy societies but well disguised in the aristocratic fashion. But in rural areas they come across as presented badly. The root of all human beings is one and therefore sanctification as to happen not only in rural parts of country but also to elite class of the urban society. Truth, Honesty, fear of conscience and righteousness are fundamental for development. Until we toil hard and grow these fundamentals it is unlikely for us to see progress in our society, Europe serves as evidence to fact wealth created on immoral grounds deceives peace of mind.

Purification of Soul

Such a discretionary judgment occurs because of worldly experience or from examination of history. That is Purification (Samskara) or civilization. The objective of civilization is twofold a) set free the feelings of the heart and spread it widely b) to highlight the discriminations in the value of various material objects. The tools available for such a refinement in life are mainly five:

i) Family – It is the heat that softens the selfish and self centered attitude of I (Me). It uses the heat of pride of being associated to Parents, Siblings, Spouse and Children to melt the entanglements of the mind, seal the cracks, strengthen the bonds, make us cry, laugh, think, perspire, relax and ripe. Therefore family is considered one among the three afflictions arising from deity or fate. House becomes the first school of discipline.

ii) Occupation – This places us in a position which is distant from our known ones and subjects us to various challenges. Our inner strength nurtures and grows because of the exercise at this place. This second school of discipline fosters the enrichment of experience and improves brilliance of our nature.

A person, who aspires to live well, will first identify a job or occupation, learn it, believe it that alone will help him to live and will try to excel in that. This excellence arises not because of his position in society or his education but the manner in which he performs in that job. The designation or status of job is irrelevant, what are more important is the intelligence, devotion and capability towards the neat execution of the job.

In Mahabharata, Yudhishtira (Dharmaraya) was questioned by the demigod (Yaksha): “Where is the dwelling place of righteousness (dharma)?”. Yudhishtira responded saying “DaakshamekaPadam Dharmam” (In the work we do we need to exhibit capability, wisdom and skill, that is the dwelling place of righteousness.) We have seen lack of such serious commitment to work and more of eye washing attitude. Nature performs her duties irrespective of being supervised or observed by any one. Beautiful flowers blossom in completely uninhabited forests not in anticipation of any appreciation but because it is its nature. Likewise if we take up the job that we have obtained and do it with all the required commitment and intelligence, our own reputation will grow.

iii) Literary Arts – This is my biggest school. If our life has to be appropriate with respect to family, occupation and other fields, education about literary arts is very much needed. There are three sections in this:

Literature – This includes Poetry, Prose, Drama, essays, stories, discourses and various such works. It brings out the numerous emotions of joy, sorrow, anger, despair which is hidden deep inside our mind and allows it to empathize with others experiences and gel with them. It further presents to us various beauties and variations in life and compels us to analyze about them. There are different levels of beauty and Literature instigates us to differentiate among them.
History – Throughout the world how people lived; what hardships they faced; in times of misery and prosperity how their minds functioned; how people reacted to words of wisdom; how it gets catalyzed to provocative talks; how great men influence behavior of others; overall how people are subjected to fate; what proportion of life is achieved through human efforts – it showcases all these and aids us in our evaluation through wisdom.
Performing Arts – This includes Music, Painting, Sculpture, Dance, Movies and other such things which make us emote. This aids Literature. They act on our hearts and bring to our experience all those emotions which are part of human nature. It helps us to develop empathy in our life.

iv)Religion – This is in position of supreme teacher for everyone. It is our faith towards God and conduct that is appropriate to it. There are none who do not align to this concept. It exists even with individuals who dwell in forests. The concept of heaven and hell resides on this premise. Generally our conduct is due to fear of God. In this way it influences the thinking of sin and good deed, thereby rectifying various practices of religion and society. In world history the influence of religion is immeasurable, in sum total this is something that we can’t ignore, neither it is necessary for us to ignore it. Supreme devotion is as pure as the love of young child; it is unconditional; full with happiness; it involves commitment to one’s religion and no animosity to other religions; having an attitude that the truth we realize may be realized by others in different form. Thirdly religion as to inculcate the mindset that we are all children of same God and need to live like brothers. One of the devotee has expressed :

Maatha cha parvathi devi pitha devo maheshwarha
Baandhavo shiva bhakthanam swadesham bhuvanathrayam.

(My mother is Goddess Parvathi and Father is Lord Shiva, all my relatives are devotees of Shiva and all three worlds are my world.) Which means compassion, service to community, charity are all live forms of righteousness.

Does this mean we do not require temples, prayers, idols, photos, meditation, chanting? All these need to be there as they help constantly remind and strengthen our beliefs. Through prayers and meditation the mind acquires tranquility and purity. Therefore all of us can observe and practice that suits our mental setup as it is good. Along with that we also need to take the broad mindedness and accommodative qualities of our religion to develop worldly brotherhood.

Distill your mind every day,
Reconciling the good and bad deeds committed every day.
Segregate the right and wrong,
Uprooting the roots of the wrong.
Following the righteous path,
Meditating on the lotus feet of supreme soul.
Renouncing the worldly pleasures,
Experience the supreme soul.
Realizing and discovering it within you.

Daily examination of soul, search of mind, every second thought of righteousness, welfare of the world is all attributes of devotion to god.

Whatever is the greatness and accomplishments of Science it has its own limitation it cannot help you to transcend in land of spirituality. If India committed fallacy of forgetting science thinking about spirituality, Europe committed the blunder of forgetting spirituality dwelling in science. Therefore, Europeans believed materialistic things and pleasure superior to spirituality and ventured into wars more often. If peace has to prevail in the entire world and give up the fear of terror, devotion to science has to be evaluated with spiritual wisdom.

Social Service

Form of God and Soul will become evident only through experience. This experience is attained only through inner sight and this is achievable only through blend of Mind and wisdom. Light emerging out of Wisdom and emotions of heart together give rise to a new light. Wisdom can be obtained through studies of various subjects but light that as to emerge out of heart has to come through interactions with society and not through self study. One should practice sympathy for difficulties of world. He has to participate in sharing the burden of the society. In process of working towards it he has to decrease his narrow mindedness and expand boundary of his soul. Only contact of society will enable him to purify his soul which is responsible for inner sight.

It is easy to sing “God is our Father; we are all one”. If we are to realize the true meaning of that in our lives; we need to engage ourselves in some social activity which does not involve yielding to petty favor requests of friends and relatives and our selfish acts. For this activity, we should not hold ourselves back until someone invites us but we have to voluntarily search for opportunities to engage. This is the path for expansion of our soul and easing us out of smaller troubles which could entrap us.

In our country there are two major avenues to engage in public activity namely i) Political, ii) Societal.

i) Politics involves thousands of things which are to be performed for good of the country which means subject related to welfare of our co-citizens. In this regard every alert human being has certain responsibilities which are the duties of citizen. The duties of citizen are mainly two fold: I) to abide by the law and order of the state ii) to continuously examine, review and express the opinion regarding function of the government. Honest conformity and Independent review are two major parts of duty of citizen.

Many people conform to law and order of the state but this is result of long practice not born out of intellect. This is a blind conformation but not arising out of independent thinking. Our conformity should emerge out of our wisdom. If we thoroughly comprehend the framework and rules of constitution and if we follow them with appropriate knowledge about it then it becomes useful.

We are still far behind in the action part of Political review. Review does not mean voice of anger or frustration. It needs support of knowledge and should not be biased or arising out of jealousy or animosity. In today’s cultured states rules and regulations are framed by citizen representatives. Selection of the citizen representative and supervising his actions are satisfactory is very important. It is a huge responsibility to elect the most capable and appropriate to Gram Panchayat, Municipality, State government and various other governing bodies. For this we need to have deep sense of understanding and unbiased view. It is duty of every citizen to earn such an understanding and impartial thinking. In this subject we are not in a position to state that our present customs and practices are fine.

After the election, there is no hold and supervision by the people on their representatives in the government. To observe the conduct of our political leaders, review and analyze their criticism and arguments in media and provide valuable suggestions are the main aspects of citizenship. If this is not properly executed people’s say in the government will get weakened and democracy will exist for namesake without the true force that can help the nation. Therefore it is important for every citizen to pay appropriate and cautious attention towards politics.

ii) Even in the social sphere there is lot of work to be done. Every village or town has one or two social bodies like the Municipality, temples, libraries, discourse centers, gymnasium, and welfare societies for improving education, health, theatre groups and such other social organizations. To become active member of such groups or form such initiatives is every individual’s duty. This leads to betterment of townships and the individual’s life gets broadened. In this process he will mingle well with the society, comprehend various individual mannerisms, mould his behavior to the society, constantly rectify oneself and expanding his mind on his own will allow his soul to grow. Social service is the daily duty related to national welfare and is the best school for education to allow growth of heart. The inspiration that is present there to research on one’s soul and opportunity to expand it is nowhere else available. The new form of electorate that needs to happen in India is through the practice of social service.

Improvement of Villages – Land Cultivation

We have already seen how villages are getting destroyed. Villages are becoming weaker due to attraction of urban cities. With the new age politics the village strength is being broken, in lure of the salaries and other comforts people from villages are moving to workplaces in factories or offices. In context of election, for sake of competing more crime is becoming rampant. There is scant attention towards the agricultural land. We are importing several essential food commodities from other countries. Is it required to fill politics to such an extent? Is it good for the people? Is it difficult to control the commotion during the election? All these are the prime questions. If we assume that there is certain amount of politics required, we need mechanisms to counter the ill effects of it. Agricultural practice is a profession which teaches people unity. Without friendship and co-operation it is hard to cultivate the land even for a day. Tilling, ploughing, cultivating, harvesting, cleaning, chafing, transporting all of them require man power. Cultivation is not a single person activity. It requires various farm equipment and other paraphernalia which needs to be available at right time. Even the cattle that are required at times required. In this way cultivation is a co-operative effort of many houses and that is the beauty of it. Therefore it develops humanity. High amount of automation and technology erodes this human bonding. Politics and elections only destroy the human relationships. We are trying to emulate cultures and practices of various other nations and attain peace of mind that needs to be curtailed. For this to be possible the task that needs to be accomplished by the educated class is big. People who are pensioners or who have taken voluntary retirement from services and who still have the capability to work need to take this up as their responsibility. Even in them, people who have lands that can be cultivated need to make up their minds to stay in villages and through their good conduct will have to transform the minds of the village citizens. One large co-operative movement, one festival and one social center can erode the philistine thinking of several individuals and lift their minds to a higher altitude.(In this regard it is very appropriate to remind ourselves of the Operation Flood started by Mr. Kurien which transformed life of several milk farmers). Every village or town has a place of worship. This can easily be made as center of activity to organize discourses, discussions on scriptures, village festivals and elate the beauty of them. This can easily kill the boredom of villages. The rampant transformation we have seen in the infrastructure related to transportation and communication further enables to provide any facility and entertainment that is available in urban cities to villages. This has to be enabled by the educated class first with the help of the government taking it up as a joint responsibility. The essential service that needs to be rendered to the nation today is the upliftment of villages. Upliftment here refers to number of people residing in villages, their health, physical strength, clean and tidy environment of their households, growth of their livestock, rejuvenation and development of lakes and ponds, primary education, medical facilities and above all this to control the migration of population from villages to urban cities. People who are physically and intellectually strong should stay in their respective villages and put their strength to use for the development. In order to enable this we need to adequately fill motivational factors in villages. A good society is the only medicine to bad politics. Welfare and Development of villages has to become a primary goal in Social service.

Larger Philosophy

If evil spirits are warded off, then it is possible to realize supreme soul. If inappropriate faith is removed from our lives then we will be able to gain wisdom of welfare. Therefore we need to first examine our individual minds and cleanse them. Baseless fears have to be discarded. Previous Karma (actions belonging to previous birth), luck, destiny and fate – such thoughts have to be distanced for a while, the world we live in is the evident destiny, human effort is the duty assigned to us by God, expansion of soul is the supreme victory – such thoughts should come to our remembrance.

In 4th Century BC, when Greek society was indulged in excessive practices of spirit, curse and occult science, Greek philosopher Diogenes erected a scripture at a place visible to entire society which read as follows:

“Don’t fear God, don’t worry about death; what’s good is easy to get, and what’s terrible is easy to endure”.

This should serve as medicine to cure different ailments that humans are afflicted with.

When we talk about heroism and human effort a word of caution needs to be said pressingly. From human effort this world will become a permanent heaven is something not suggested by anyone. There are many things that are improbable to solve through our intellect and science. Lust, anger, jealousy and attachment can be removed from human character is a farfetched thought. When they spring up in our minds, to subdue them in such a fashion that they do not outgrow their limits is possible only through moral science or political system but cannot be completely uprooted from humans. Because in reality the seeds of such thoughts are embedded by nature. In the same manner diseases, old age and death cannot be completely removed through science. All of them have a definite place in the order of creation. In the man’s quest and search of nature, nature constantly conspires for his destruction. The fate of human world is something that cannot be newly written by anyone. On our slate there have been many writings of chalk and coal. Some of them can be removed while some of them continue to stay in a hidden fashion as dents on slate. Our present situation is unlike this but a manifestation of thousands of years of our history. Therefore the changes that we conceive and wish to make to some our old practices is not happening at the rate which we desire. Our vision is progress but that is something that cannot be achieved in hurry. Progress has to be steady and long sustaining one and therefore has to start from educational system and orderly progress to encompass all walks of life. Progress achieved through patience, independent thinking, valuation of pros and cons, humility and appropriate examination will be a successful one.

Progress – A Lengthy Act

Progress is not a one day’s act in a lifetime. It should be act of every moment and every day. There is no good thing in our lives which can be achieved in one single day and which can be enjoyed throughout our lives. Hygiene, Health, Wealth, Friendship, love of relatives – for all of them we need to work on a daily basis. After several hours of taking bath we need to cleanse our body again, after few hours of taking food we need to feed ourselves, after certain period of getting salary we need to again attain it and so is progress. If we stop thinking of our progress we decline (Stagnation eventually leads to death) and it is man’s fate. Continuous efforts and refinement of our lives is daily duty.

A scheme in hands of human being is just like a garland in the hands of monkey, no matter how good a state’s system and financial progress is planned, some feature of human conduct poisons it. As we aim to shoot at fruit hanging from tree it no way guarantees that our throw will strike the fruit and bring it down. With whatever wisdom and caution we try to conduct ourselves in executing our duties there is bound to be some short coming in the end result. This is the principle of progress. Even the best automobile will have its parts worn out as they are continuously used. Space objects like Planets also slow down after sometime due to continuous revolution and rotation due to loss of energy. Likewise, our social system, practice, principles and laws become redundant and outdated after certain time which no one can prevent. Therefore, all of us need to be ever prepared to face and bear challenges to a certain extent. As is our duty to surmount the challenges with enthusiastic effort so is our duty to patiently and bravely endure it. Patience and Human effort are not two different situations but they need to blend into one. Patience does not mean inaction and effort does not mean fight with fit of rage. Patience is to have balanced and calm mind without tumultuous emotions of anger; constantly disallowing the mind to be lethargic and inactive with thoughts of progress and engaging outwardly in rightful action is effort. In this way human effort is a kind of education of soul.

Our Life is Peepal Tree

Our ancestors have always compared our life to Peepal tree. Peepal tree lives for a fairly long time. In spite of leaving for hundreds of years it does not appear to be the same today as it was yesterday. A branch which appears fresh and filled with life will appear weak and dry after few weeks. A branch which appears worn and weeding out now is sprouting with new leaves in the very next week. Our human life is also similar with progressive intellect, wisdom, development, enthusiasm on one side and on other side we have wagered mind, effort in vain and complete lack of enthusiasm. There is no space anywhere for complete greed or despair. Rising, falling, rolling, spreading somehow the river of life goes on at all times. Why should we fear and loose heart? For sake of education and enrichment of soul we need to aim and achieve progress. In that we should not have greed, ill temper, and unnecessary excitement for fruits of our efforts and at the same time it is not good to have laziness, lack of human effort. Our activity should continue uninterrupted like act of nature, celestial activities and sprouts of plants.

If God exists or not is not really relevant. Our life is the primary evidence for us. Our life is remembrance of God. In this way it is appropriate we respect our life as prima facie evidence of God’s activity. Life is gift by God; beautifying Life is our gratitude to God. Life’s progress, refinement and glorification are not only aspiration of people who are indulged in comfort and luxury but also the message of Vedas and Upanishads. Our great sage Vidyaranya who simultaneously overlooked responsibility of being the chief mentor to Vijayanagar Empire and Head pontiff of the prestigious, illustrious Sringeri Shankar Mutt said in Panchadashi “jnAninA charitum shakyam samyak rAjyAdi loukikam” which means it is very well possible for the Jnani (enlightened) to engage in empirical duties such as administering a Kingdom. There is no opposition to worldly activities and Vedic philosophies, practice of Upanishads and Vedas is best employed for selfless service to betterment of society is evident from life of Vidyaranya.

Appendix

Caution required with respect to Science

Science has progressed well and conquered new frontiers unveiling many new secrets of nature but we still have many unanswered questions with reference to life. Human life’s questions are more introspective in nature where as the feats of science are external. We are no way close to use science to answer them.

Every discipline of science is still incomplete in reaching the complete potential. Physics which is considered as king among all sciences is still exploring the various constituents of atom and its structure. Advancement in life sciences is just breaking grounds and making a paradigm shift. Psychology is yet to establish one strong foundation for answering majority of questions.

How did life originate from the inanimate substances such as earth, water and air? How did mind originate? These two questions are still answered.

The reach of these sciences currently is like you have a well which is having water 60 feet deep from surface and rope which is 60 feet in length. Rope can only help you to touch the surface of water but it is not enough to fetch you to water going inside. It is just sufficient to touch exteriors of our life. Power, Telecommunications, Health sciences and Information Technology all have influenced and changed our external lives but not have impacted our internal life.

The state of science is still half baked, half ripe and many of the principles are there to change and we cannot extrapolate them to every walk of life. There are various principles and customs which have helped to build the social structure of this country. On one hand we have to use science to remove from root some of the social practices which have been evils such as child marriage, female infanticide, blind faith and superstitions but we also have to be extremely cautious not to use them against institutions such as marriage which is a healthier way of social living. Politics on the other hand should not take advantage of these scientific advancements for driving personal agenda and goals. Change is very important for all our lives but change has to be accompanied with proper scientific reasoning.

Takeaway Note :

It was irrerestible for me to complete my humble attempt of this translation work without this takeaway note which is a brilliant message of Swami Vivekananda, one of the prolific thinker of 20th Century which India was blessed with. These words serve as icing on the cake and encapsulates the message of this book:

“The history of the world is the history of a few men who had faith in themselves. That faith calls out the divinity within. You can do anything. You fail only when you do not strive sufficiently to manifest infinite power.

Anything that makes you weak physically, intellectually, and spiritually; reject as poison; there is no life in it, it cannot be true. Truth is strenthening, truth is purity, truth is all-knowledge; truth must be enlightening and must be invigorating.

Let us all work hard, my brethren; this is no time for sleep. On our work depends the coming of the India of the future…”